Thank you everybody, good morning, I'm Sarah Nadi, I'm an associate professor at the University of
Alberta, and today I'll talk to you about some of the research my group and I have done to
hopefully avoid some of the frustrating experiences some of you might be getting
when using the library and its API or application programming interface. So let's take an example of
what such an experience would be like. So let's say Alice here is a developer, she's working
on a web application, she's using microprofile, which is a set of specifications and APIs for
developing microservices-based applications, and just kind of a simple test, she wants to
define an OpenAPI definition for one of her endpoints. So she finds this annotation OpenAPI
definition, you know, follows what she finds and thinks everything will be great, but really
no change is reflected in the API specification. She keeps reading the documentation trying to
figure out what's going on, can't figure it out, so as most of us will do turns to her favorite
resource Stack Overflow and post the question. And the answer comes back saying, you know what,
there we go, try putting the annotation on a JAX-RS application class. So in other words,
this annotation only works if it's put on a class that extends Application. And so this is not really
a hypothetical example, this is really from Stack Overflow, and kind of from the comment here we see
oh yeah, that solution worked, unfortunately it just doesn't seem well documented. And I'm sure
some of you ran into such problems with different types of libraries and different APIs you've used.
and the issue is that there's really kind of these three worlds, or three points of view on API. There's
the API designer, what they wanted people to do, how they expected people to use the API, so, their
intentions. There's the API documentation which hopefully has all these intentions documented,
and then there's the API users' understanding based on reading the documentation, maybe based on, kind
of, other information of similar libraries they have used. And in an ideal world all these three
would be kind of overlapping and we wouldn't have any problems. But in practice things look somewhat
like that. And it's at these boundaries that these problems happen. I'm just gonna use this.
And these problems are kind of types of bugs or types of errors, and they're very specific. So the
problem I'm talking about today I refer to as API misuses, and this is the incorrect or unexpected
behavior of an API or, like, unexpected behavior you get because of misusing the API or not correctly
using it because of some problems like we've seen: hidden intentions or undocumented intentions.
And so somebody can say, okay, but there's tools that can help me with that. So there's a lot of
tools out there that scan your code and point to some problems of very commonly used APIs or
very commonly used libraries. I'll say that's true, and the way these tools work is that they focus
on common mistakes or bug patterns. So basically somebody in the background, whether this is the
API designer or API expert, somebody very familiar with it, seeing the problem several times says, okay,
this is a usage rule, this is something we need to document, this is something we need these tools to
check for. And this is great, but it's also a lot of manual effort and reliance on these experts
to encode these in the rules. And so the question becomes, can we discover these API usage rules or
these expectations automatically? And we thought, let's set out to do this. And so what we did was
we looked at client code, so basically projects that use this library or API, and lots of it, and we
looked through the API usages, so let's say very simply here is an API that connects the database, we look at
how everybody's using it, and we look for frequent patterns there. So we say, okay, here there's the
pattern, you connect to the database, you execute the query, and you close the database connection.
And so the idea is that using this pattern we can find things that deviate from the pattern. So in
this specific case we would flag this third usage here as an API misuse, something that deviated from
this API usage pattern. And so we wanted to see how this works in practice. And so we took a set of - a
benchmark, which is a set of known API misuses we have, and we said, okay, let's measure how many
or what percentage of these known misuses can our detector find based on this pattern-based
detector, so that's recall, and what percentage of the things that we report to the developer,
the misuses that we flag, are actually real misuses people will care about, so that's precision.
And in practice we found that, okay, we can detect 42% of the benchmark but our precision
is around 34% which means that one out of every three warnings we give a developer is probably
something they don't really want to fix. And the reasons for that are things like idioms,
so sometimes you mine patterns that are just idioms, people are frequently using them but it
doesn't mean that those who don't use it, it's a problem, right, and so, so far I presented these
kind of two worlds. There's pattern mining, which is completely automated and you can use it as a basis
for rules and misuse detection, but the problem is, it suffers from this low precision and recall,
depending on, kind of, which APIs and so on. And then there's writing API usage rules in these
tools, so manually encoding them, but that's kind of time consuming and relies on so much effort.
And so what we ended up doing is trying to kind of combine
the best of these two worlds. So we want to make it easier for the API developer,
sorry, the API designer to encode these expectations quickly, and we want to make it easier
for API users to have checkers for them that can, you know, tell them if they've done something wrong.
And so we do a slight change in this pipeline in that we introduce the human in the loop approach.
So basically we start with the same idea of, we're going to mine these patterns, but we say
these are candidate rules, these are starting points for rule authoring. And the thing is, we
want to give them to API designers in a format that's easy for them to understand and easy for
them to change and say oh yeah, that's something I actually want to be checked, or no, ignore this.
And so we designed this rule validation tool, and I'll show you in a minute how it works,
where the API designer can go through all these candidate rules and say, okay, this is actually
a specification or a rule that I want people to adhere to, or this is something I don't care
about, or this is the best practice. Once we have these API usage rules we automatically generate
checks from them, so static analysis checks that we ship in a easy to use tool, basically
a Maven plugin that I'll show in a minute, and then you can just use this to scan developers'
code and flag any API misuses or any problems that they have in their code using this right.
So let's take a look at how kind of this looks like from both sides. So as an API designer, oh
I'm sorry this resolution here is pretty bad, okay, hopefully you can see something there.
If you have on the left hand side here the rule authoring editor, which presents these rules
in an English-like domain specific language, so for example, Class X, if Class X has annotation Foo
then it must have annotation Bar, for example. And on the right hand side is the code that reflects
what code would look like for this rule. So you see both kind of an English description and code.
And so the idea is that here the developer would - the API expert would look at these
rules and then decide, okay, let me just check this documentation quickly, what was this API
again, okay, yeah, so this is not a rule, I'm going to skip this, then look at this and say okay, that's
a good starting point, but it's not exactly what we want, let me just edit this a bit, and you can see
it reflecting there, and once I'm happy with it I'm going to confirm that this is a rule.
One of the other ones maybe just say, oh that's a rule already, I don't need to change anything for
it. And maybe for some, this is a best practice, it's not like really a violation. We also have
documentation on how to use this and kind of what the different parts of this domain
specific language is that you can check out and then just kind of things to help you author the
rules like formatting and so on, so, like just make it look pretty. Okay so then you've went through
these candidate rules that have been mined, some of them are good, some of them you've edited, now
you have a set of confirmed rules that you want, you know, anybody using your library to adhere to.
and so once you've done that we automatically generate, basically a Maven plug-in that
the client developer can use, so the API user can use, so all they need is to say, you know, scan my
code using this violation detection, and it's going to tell them what's wrong with the code. So in this
case there's a class that has a function with annotation "query", and in that case the class for
this to work must have an annotation "GraphQL API" and it's telling you what's missing there,
line numbers and so on. So basically what this kind of pipeline does is that, we are starting a
conversation between the API designer and the API user, and it's an automated conversation that can
go on, right. So by giving the API designer - telling them how people are using their API - helping them,
you know, create these expectations, make them more explicit, they can then help the API user
use this correctly and the cycle can go on, like, as the API evolves you can figure out, okay, have
people changed how they're using this, what are the frequent usages, and in the end this, you know, makes
us all happy because it avoids buggy software. And before I wrap up, I just want to thank everybody
who's been involved in this work, whether students in my group, external collaborators, also our IBM
collaborators who we worked with on the microprofile stuff. And with that I'd like to thank
you all, encourage you to, you know, try this out. We have two sets of tools: one that focuses on
really, kind of, API usage patterns inside methods, so things like the close database
connection, so it focuses on control and data flow, and another that's the whole pipeline that focuses
on annotation-based Java usage patterns, misuses and validating those. Thank you so much, I'd be
happy to take questions or you know chat during lunch or coffee breaks. Thanks a lot.